hi I'm Chad walquist I'm an architect here at
paler I've been working in the data analytics
and AI space for the last 15 plus years I have
seen these architectures and systems evolve over
time and the enterprise software landscape is
more fragmented now than ever it has turned
into a true Tower of Babel where no one can
seem to communicate or work together different
scaling functions security mechanisms data format
instead each promotes their own isolated interest
at the expense of the system as a whole however
though in Enterprise it's a system of systems
I see some of the most viral posts online about
these hyper complex Market Maps open- Source tools
and VC backed vendors pitching their easy to sell
box on someone's architecture diagram the problem
with this is the focus is not on how the system
as a whole will add value to your organization but
how each point solution can be sold Enterprises
are already facing increased complexity and now
you layer in AI on top of that what I see
is AI adding a nonlinear stepwise increase
in that complexity to the entire software stack
threatening to topple this Tower when customers
come to AIP con or analysts talk to our customers
with AIP use cases in production they ask the same
thing how is paler the only one enabling AI in
production operations we've spent the last 20
plus years in operational use cases in the
toughest environments in the world we have
hundreds of our forward deployed Engineers on the
ground at the edge with our customers eating the
pain and building the product that matters to
our customers not for an architecture diagram
so how are we doing this today I'm going
to walk you through how we approach this
differently all right before we get into
the architecture we're going to show you
from an operational application back to the
sources so you have a point of reference so
this is a workshop application of a supply
chain control tower that allows me to build
these data Rich applications that are
bidirectional and right back I can take
action through these applications it's not
just a report we also have ai agents embedded
in here so I have agents seeing and looking
as data is coming in through my platform and
helping me reason through how to resolve different
issues whether they can do it autonomously or even
exit and ask for human help this is AI and human
teaming if we then look at those agents you can
see here this is AIP logic I actually have
the ability to create system promps I give
it access to tools I can I give it access to
data I can give it access to functions or it
can apply actions or take actions on my behalf
I can call forecasting functions all of this in
one interface and I can then even switch out which
models I want from a model catalog that I can pop
with a default set or I can even bring my own
model endpoints or my own finetune models if I
would like and then each logic block can actually
use different model so the right model for the
different proms so you can mix and match and use
them together this is super powerful and then if
we look at workflow Builder here this is that same
application and all of the ontology objects that
it's using to actually represent this application
which is great and the cool thing is that I can
also take those same functions I build in this
application and then build a custom application
custom integration on top of their so in this
example I also have on that same set of ontology
objects a Titan satellite tasking application
that's built on our ontology SDK the ontology
SDK here actually generates a custom SDK based on
your ontology objects it creates the documentation
everything you need to know and the packages
to integrate on top of ontology even pick your
language of choice here very cool then if we get
back to the ontology when we talk about ontology
object this is actually an ontology object
normally you would have a dimension a data
warehouse that is a tabular data set you can see
how rich this is I also have streams I have link
data I have geospatial I have schematics I can
have video images all of that in one ontology
object no longer just tabular data how do we
populate onology objects the ontology objects are
the blue objects over here on the right these are
the nouns and verbs that make up the data logic
and actions of your business so that you can make
decisions so how do we hydrate that that's through
all these pipelines you can see running here here
so these different data pipelines can be proc code
or low code so you can run python Java SQL to
transform your data across these pipelines to
hydrate these objects you can also have multimodal
data I can look here and I have snowflake so I can
register data through virtual tables from your
own data warehouse without copying it I can get
apis I can get sap I can use our hyper Auto
to actually build these transforms for me I
also have streaming data from opcua all of those
things com together in one single pan of glass
into these ontology objects that I build these
data Rich applications all right that's top to
bottom this is the paler AI mesh architecture
these eight core capabilities are essential
for delivering true Enterprise AI at scale
today we'll explore how these components
integrate in our interoperable with your existing
landscape starting with outcomes in mind we have
a product Building Services there are two main
areas first up is our pre-built AI products we
have AIP now offerings that can be installed
in minutes integrated with your unique data
logic and actions and then customize as needed
this is an easy button for Enterprise apps we
also have build with AIP a set of developer Focus
starter packs to accelerate time to delivery of
things like LM Vision models to extract data from
unstructured sources it's pretty cool for custom
build applications we offer a suite of tools for
analytics whether it be Time series geospatial
AI assisted deep Dives additionally we provide
operational app building ranging from low code to
full Pro code and even mixed reality our developer
tool chain focuses on getting your work into
production whether through the ontology SDK for
fully custom apps or Integrations a Marketplace to
consume from or contribute to or even integrated
devops tool chain the key theme Here is building
integrated AI experiences and getting them into
production as quickly and safely as possible
all of the analytics and applications within
AIP are built upon the ontology the ontology
is designed to represent the decisions in an
Enterprise not merely the data IT addresses
the core challenge that every organization faces
executing the best possible decisions often in
real time amidst constantly changing internal and
external conditions the ontology facilitates deep
TOA interoperability with existing Enterprise
systems so this setup enables the rapid
development of operational applications with
AI teaming in addition to Conventional business
intelligence and analytics workflows every
decision can be broken down into three core
components data logic and actions so we about data
these are the relevant facts or truths about your
world the nouns and verbs of your operation that
form the context for each decision then logic this
encompasses the organizational and business rules
that act as the guard rails for your decisions
each includes understanding of the probabilities
of certain outcomes under different assumptions
past experiences in similar situations and
inputs from forecast and optimization models
and then actions these represent the kinetics
or the effects of a decision they describe
how the decision manifests in the real world
and the detailed steps needed to translate a
decision with an AIP to a tangible outcome in
a production setting okay so by automatically
integrating all these components the ontology not
only simplifies but also accelerates the journey
from decision making to real world action this
is key to enabling AI as the ontology grounds
LMS in the truth of your business operations
and decisions this is crucial because when
you're modeling the digital twin of your business
process in the ontology it's not just data it's a
digitized business process that is the backbone
of your operation that also acts as the semantic
layer for LMS to bring reasoning and automation
capabilities all of this is secured with a full
audit Trail explainable Chain of Thought
reasoning and gives a level of transparency
that human and AI work together this shared
decision model is key to adoption integrity at
scale all right moving down the stack from the
ontology we have data services AI services and
workflow Services let's dive a little bit deeper
into the data services we think of this in three
main areas connectivity integration and management
you can ingest and process in batch micro batch
CDC and streaming as a first class citizen
so AI thrives on stream data for realtime
feedback loops and we'll get to that more in the
AI services in a minute you have over 150 outof
the boox connections plus the ability to build
your own connector I have yet to find a system
we can't connect to our hyper Auto Tool automates
data Transformations turning complex systems like
sap into usable ontologies within hours and days
pipeline Builder it's from multimodal data think
of structured unstructured media PDF images stream
building llm processing blocks for inline context
and reason all of this on an ultra scalable
infrastructure all of these tools support data
as code allow me to Branch my data along with my
code versioning lineage tracking all of this built
upon the same unified and security and governance
even this in the data services we have AIP assist
integrated for help with pipeline building
air resolution offering up code suggestions
and explanations in real time if we take a step
over to AI Services we have three main areas model
connectivity model train in model operation in
model connectivity we have many ways to integrate
models that you've built bought or download
an open source one you can host models in AIP
externally and register them bring containerized
model that have robust dependencies or select from
an open source model that you can use out of the
box the idea here is any model anywhere can be
integrated into a workflow in AIP then to model
training you have a secure hosted jupyter lab
notebook R Studio code workbooks you can even use
pipeline builds or with a containerized training
the idea is you have all the tools you need inside
the secure Enclave of AIP to prepare cleanse your
data and then securely train your models lastly
is model operations let's get it to production
at scale right we have the concept of modeling
objectives that facilitates multiple scientists
and Builders building submitting and comparing
models against each other or scoring against a
thirdparty model as well all towards the same goal
of a better model you can evaluate release host
and monitor your models all all of this comes
together in an integrated nnml Ops framework
again built on the same security and governance
foundations now in workflow Services we have three
areas workflow building decision orchestration and
Edge integration starting in workflow building we
have an aptly named workflow Builder that
we showed you earlier modelbased execution
process mining automation framework in decision
orchestration we have batch CDC and streaming
right back along with even native client right
back like sap boopies then in Edge Integrations
we have Edge pipelines Edge mod models and Edge
objects bring your own device or Apollo manage
devices the idea here is we meet you where you are
and this is super powerful to model your business
processes next up we have security and governance
which spans infrastructure platform and Enterprise
security this includes automated security patching
continuous monitoring secure model hubs role-based
marking based and purpose-based access controls
approval Frameworks and even granular audit and
logging and at the base it's Apollo of product
we developed to deploy and manage software like
AIP and Foundry Apollo orchestrates hundreds of
microservices enabling quick deployment updates
and even things out to the edge this foundational
erir ensures our forward deployed Engineers can
innovate rapidly and deploy new features for
you at the edge as we talked about before this
is just a small slice of what there is but if you
think about it just these two bottom boxes alone
this would be a myriad of tools that you have to
stitch together and everything above it would be
even harder to implement AI needs this secure
Foundation across the board and we need tools
like Apollo to deploy and innovate rapidly all
right I know that was a speedrun through the AI
mesh architecture but I hope you get the point
that at the end of the day it's about how do I
drive outcomes in this integrated platform with
a unified security governance and deployment
model allows you to move quickly the speed of
your thought to drive outcomes not worry about
stitching all these tools together and how do
you do it in a safe and secure way so when you
layer gen AI on top of this these models are very
unpredictable they hallucinate how do you manage
that how do you evaluate how do you pick the right
model for The Right Use cases how do you do that
in a production Manner and manage it over time
all these tool sets only add an extra level of
complexity across your entire Tex stack now this
is where the AI mesh comes in because it also
integrates with your existing tool sets so we can
integrate through apis SDK it's an unwalled Garden
for your Enterprise so at the end of the day if
it's not in uction it's not adding value [Music]